TAPOPRIYA MAJUMDAR

Montréal, Canada \diamond (438) 505-7182 tapopriya.majumdar@umontreal.ca

SUMMARY

Canadian **permanent resident** with more than three years' experience in Machine Learning and Big Data, and a background in Mathematics and Computer Science from elite universities. Proficient in python, R, SQL, PyTorch, Keras, spark and hive technologies.

TECHNICAL STRENGTHS

Scalable Data Hadoop, Hive, AWS EC2 and S3, Spark (Spark SQL, MLlib)

Operating Systems Ubuntu Linux, OS X

Computer Languages Python, R

Machine Learning scikit-learn, NumPy, pandas, NLTK, forecast, dplyr

Neural Network Keras, PyTorch, TensorFlow (basic)

Data Visualization Tableau, matplotlib, Seaborn, ggplot2

Databases SQL (Oracle SQL Developer), NoSQL (MongoDB)

Miscellaneous Git, agile, docker, tmux, LATEX

EXPERIENCE

Scalian Inc. March 2020 -

Senior Data Scientist Montréal, Canada

Working on a distributional reinforcement learning project

Canadian National

July 2019 - December 2019

Montréal, Canada

Senior Data Scientist (Contract Position)

Worked on an object tracking project to detect signals and people from a live video feed

Université de Montréal

January 2019 -

Graduate Researcher

Montréal, Canada

Natural Language Processing researcher in the **Recherche Appliquée en Linguistique Informatique** laboratory, currently working in Neural Machine Translation and Language Modelling

Fidelity Investments

June 2017 - July 2018

Associate Software Engineer / Data Scientist

Bangalore, India

Worked in the following projects:

- PSS Optimization: Optimizing the number of associates required in a unit using time series analysis
- Detect and Repair: Classification of tickets using machine learning techniques on text descriptions
- EDA Tool: Browser based data summarization and visualization program using big data techniques
- Data Exfiltration: An anomaly detection algorithm to analyze IP addresses and check for improper system access

InterpretOmics India Pvt Ltd

May 2016 - May 2017

Data Scientist / Statistician

Bangalore, India

Completed the following projects:

- Drug Target Discovery: Constraint-based modeling techniques on genome-scale metabolic models to find potential biomarkers that affects the growth in the diseased cells alone.
- Patient Stratification: Machine learning techniques are used to stratify disease sub-types/groups from the population using biomarkers (gene expression) and clinical markers (phenotype).

Galvanize, Inc

Data Science Fellow

October 2015 - February 2016 San Francisco, CA

Completed a rigorous 12-week program implementing a variety of data analysis methods and machine learning techniques.

Ohio State University

September 2008 - April 2015

Graduate Teaching Assistant

Columbus, OH

Recitation instructor and grader for various undergraduate courses

EDUCATION

Université de Montréal, Canada

(ongoing)

Master's in Computer Science (Concentration in Artificial Intelligence)

• Master's Thesis: Working on Language Modelling and Neural Machine Translation.

Ohio State University, USA

May 2015

PhD in Mathematics

(all but dissertation)

• Research Topic: Geometric (Elliptic) Partial Differential Equations. Worked on finding solutions to Dirichlet type fully nonlinear equations on Riemannian manifolds.

Université Bordeaux 1, France & Università di Padova, Italy

February 2008

ALGANT Master in Mathematics

• Master's Thesis: Studied the large sieve technique in Analytic Number Theory and its application to the Bombieri-Vinogradov Theorem.

Chennai Mathematical Institute, India

August 2005

B.Sc. in Mathematics (Hons.) Minor in Computer Science

THEORETICAL KNOWLEDGE

Regression & Classification Linear Regression, Logistic Regression, SVM, Random Forest,

LDA, Boosting, Naive Bayes, kNN

Dimensionality Reduction PCA, SVD

Clusteringk-Means, Hierarchical, DBSCANTime SeriesARIMA, Exponential Smoothing

Text Analytics Smoothing, POS-Tagging, Text Embeddings, Parsing

Neural Networks CNN, RNN, LSTM, Transformer, VAE, GAN

ACADEMIC ACHIEVEMENTS

- Ranked 5^{th} at the CSIR-UGC NET Examination for Mathematics in December 2016. This is a national level test in India undertaken by tens of thousands of applicants to determine eligibility for college and university level lecturership.
- Recipient of the prestigious **Erasmus Mundus** scholarship awarded by the European Union while attending my Master's.
- Selected with full tuition waiver and a scholarship to the Bachelor's Programme at Chennai Methematical Institute through a national level entrance test. It is one of the topmost undergraduate programs for Mathematics in India with less than 2% acceptance rate.

PERSONAL

Immigration Status Permanent Resident

Citizenship Indian

Languages English (proficient), Bengali (mother tongue), Hindi (proficient)

Interests Reading, Travelling, Racquetball, Classic Rock